<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--
Copyright 2007-2008 the original author or authors.

Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->

<document>
	<properties>
		<title>GWE - Grid Wizard Enterprise</title>
		<author email="mruiz@ncmir.ucsd.edu">Marco Ruiz</author>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<release version="0.7.3-alpha" date="03-02-2009" description="Ninth Alpha Release. New tools and productivity features.">
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-">
				First working draft of the new "Results Browser": infrastructure for local daemons and integration into Web Control Panel. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-">
				Redesign and implementation of P2EL compilation cycles: compilation -> system resolution -> runtime resolution.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-">
				New order "permutation dumps" features: CSV and generated commands of order submitted. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-">
				New server side (user API) preview order feature and integration with the client side preview (macro expansions) available in the Web Control Panel. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-">
				Enhancements to "regExp" P2EL function to support specific matching interest.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-">
				Configurable resource managers per daemon to take precedence over the resource manager auto-discovery process.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-">
				New resource manager driver to support clusters managed by "bsub" based systems (LSF, Lava).
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-">
				New "compute node connection timeout" feature and configuration option. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="fix" issue="GWE-155">
				Fix stalling allocations for "local" resource manager. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-">
				New P2EL macros categorization infrastructure and integration into the Web Control Panel.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-">
				Option to select daemon bundle type to deploy for installation. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="fix" issue="GWE-">
				Fix key store encryption problems for 64-bits machines.
			</action>
		</release>
		
		<release version="0.7.2-alpha" date="02-04-2009" description="Eight Alpha Release. Productivity and robustness features.">
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-166">
				Configurable HTTP authentication.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-167">
				Support for special "root" variable for P2EL macros. Legacy macros update to take advantage of this variable. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-168">
				P2EL macros to support XNAT operations through the REST API.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-164">
				Configurable daemon's product installation and operational database path. Replaced 'gweHome' from key store configuration.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-162, GWE_85">
				Secure read of passwords and pass phrases and encryption of the complete key store. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-169">
				New P2EL value generator function: text file parser. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-165">
				Infrastructure enhancements to the test host feature and integration into GWE terminal.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-9">
				Files related to allocations disposed are now stored in a special workspace folder. New option in the web control panel to clean up this folder. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-76">
				Delete order feature implementation and integration into "GWE Terminal" and "GWE Web Control Panel". 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-41">
				Pause and resume order feature implementation and integration into "GWE Terminal" and "GWE Web Control Panel". 
			</action>
		</release>
		
		<release version="0.7.1-alpha" date="12-30-2008" description="Seventh Alpha Release. Infrastructure and new tools.">
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-138">
				New "GWE Web Control Panel" sub-project. Full feature, rich web client application to manage a GWE Grid.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-124">
				Full feature P2EL macro module. Includes some out-of-the-box macros.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-134">
				New P2EL value generator function: XPath based parser. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-139">
				Resource handle factory infrastructure to replace the convoluted drivers framework. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-140">
				P2EL inline editor in the GWE Terminal application.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-141">
				Registry for host tunnels to keep a better control on when and what ports should be tunneled.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="fix" issue="GWE-142">
				IP port conflicts created by opening tunnels on ports without even checking if they are being used. Uses the new tunnels registry.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-143">
				Client sessions registry to replace hardcoded the grid controller "single session per client" functionality.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-144">
				More data available to the clients through opening more APIs and capturing more data related to the execution of jobs.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-145">
				Keystore test feature using test hosts per authentication info.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-146">
				Logging infrastructure (to make logging level configurable per application).
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-147">
				"Hasher" type of P2EL value space generator functions: hexadecimal MD5 calculator and UUID random generator.
			</action>
		</release>
		
		<release version="0.7.0-alpha" date="12-01-2008" description="Sixth Alpha Release. Major reachitecture.">
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-127">
				Replaced multi-user paradigm (and its associated extra security layer, user workspace resolution, user virtual file system resolution, etc). 
				A GWE daemon per user will now be used instead. This will be far easier to use and provides more robustness by relying on the OS multi-user features.    
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-127">
				Consolidation of all operational data under workspace (virtual file system, generated scripts, processes results, job managers submission files, logs, etc) 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-128">
				GWE level login will transparently reuse the SSH credentials. Replaced the old explicit GWE login.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-86">
				Single daemon services registry for multiple daemons running in a host - uniqueness scheme for registering services based on daemon's installation path. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-32">
				Daemon auto/silent installer. More robust than the previous one and doesn't require any manual intervention. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-98">
				Simplified, cleaner configuration.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-136">
				Configurable P2EL variables per daemon.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-126">
				"Local cluster" driver. It emulates a cluster out of the local machine. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-135">
				Configurable job managers submission templates.  
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-137">
				New (optional) feature for the P2EL download function to auto-decompress downloaded files.  
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-89">
				Framework to support order execution profiles to configure execution behavior (first draft).
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-100">
				Capabilities for job retries and failures tracking (using the execution profiles framework).
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-83">
				Dramatic increase in robustness and performance in the routines for agent failover and recovery and daemon and agent launching.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-84">
				Ignore SSH host keys verifications.  
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-129">
				Slicer integration updated with all the current features.  
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="fix" issue="GWE-24">
				New HTTP driver based on core java. The commons vfs library has nasty multi-threading deadlocks issues.   
			</action>
		</release>
	
		<release version="0.6.4-alpha" date="08-27-2008" description="Fifth Alpha Release. Feature and maintenance release.">
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-117">
				Generic parser framework based on regular expression rules (as infrastructure for P2EL version 2).
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="remove" issue="GWE-110">
				P2EL version 1 and its integration with GWE.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-110">
				P2EL version 2. Language design (syntax and semantics), module design, implementation and documentation.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-112">
				Migration of functionality of old P2EL into the new version.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-120">
				Integration of P2EL version 2 with GWE.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-113">
				Implementation of multidimensional variables features (variables of type array) into the new version of P2EL.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-114">
				Implementation of variables co-dependency features into the new version of P2EL. This has the nice 
				side effect of allowing function invocation aggregation functionality.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-116">
				Upload/download functions to support directories in addition to just files. 	  	 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-118">
				Redesign and re-implementation P2EL "dir" function (old "expand") to make it more versatile by allowing matching patterns per file branches. 	  	 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-116">
				"grep" like function for P2EL.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-121">
				Friendlier error messages for user mistakes while using GWE generic clients.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-122">
				More status information added to the generic client query commands.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.6.3-alpha" date="06-19-2008" description="Fourth Alpha Release. Feature and maintenance release.">
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-7">
				Full PKI (public key infrastructure) authentication support, including private key passphrase prompting on shell based applications when necessary. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-77">
				Utility to read private key's passphrases from the prompt of shell based applications. Usage of this utility to add its feature to the generic GWE clients. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="fix" issue="GWE-22">
				Misleading exception messages (output in the generic GWE clients) have been replaced with actual user and system errors.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-56">
				Full feature framework to support pluggable, life cycle based, P2EL functions.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-58">
				Abstract resource stager framework built as an extension of the P2EL function framework. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-57">
				Re-implementation of file staging feature as pluggable functions into the new resource stager framework. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-81">
				Performance improvement of core file transfer routines. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-55">
				Support for P2EL anonymous variables, as a P2EL function. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-3">
				Support for P2EL wildcard support to traverse on file names, as a P2EL function.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-75">
				Increased robustness of condor resource manager driver discovery by using condor_version instead of condor_status. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-80">
				Revamped Slicer3 CLMP framework to increase flexibility and robustness to the Slicer3 CLMP framework. Motivated mainly 
				to be able to reuse it to create the side project "Slicer3 Chain Modules Engine". 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="fix" issue="GWE-82">
				Job result stored in the DB compressed to prevent it from reaching the 32K size limit (DB updates were crashing because of this).   
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add">
				New online forum for the GWE community to share their experiences and comments.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update">
				"P2EL Guide" and "Configuration Guide" updated according to changes. 
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.6.2-alpha" date="04-07-2008" description="Third Alpha Release. Feature and maintenance release.">
			<action dev="mruiz" type="fix" issue="GWE-10">
				Processing of jobs in compute nodes using the user that submitted the job rather than the user running the GWE daemon.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-19">
				Regular and administrator user domain integrated with GWE level authentication and authorization.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-39">
				Rich set of features added to the terminal application (powered by JLine). Among these are: masked  
				password capturing, inline command edition, command history, tab completion and tab suggestion.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-46">
				Major refactoring of the configuration API for tool integration. It has been made simpler, more robust and flexible. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-50">
				New startup service beacon on the GWE daemon to report initialization progress to the remote client 
				installing/configuring/launching it.  
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="fix" issue="GWE-62">
				SSH tunnels opened using logged in users authentication information and not that of the user running the GWE daemon.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="fix" issue="GWE-63">
				Condor system id retrieved in the condor driver.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-64">
				Re-architect package manager and application factory as grid level factories by extending the driver 
				framework (GridBundleManager and GridOSAppManager).
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-65">
				GWE security domain authorization layer module using AOP security interceptors.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-66">
				Simplified session and accessor API for tool integration
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-67">
				Integrated simplified session and accessor API with shell based applications (terminal and command) and slicer CLMPs
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-68">
				GWE security authentication layer module using hierarchy encryption (daemon encryptor, over user passwords MD5 hash, over user sensitive data) 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-69">
				Security authentication utility module using MD5 based symmetric keys and AES encryption.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-70">
				Increased robustness and flexibility of the utility to install, configure and launch a GWE daemon.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-71">
				Added GWE authentication information capturing capabilities to Slicer3 CLMP modules.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-72">
				User translation layer module for pre-processing (downloading files) and post processing (uploading files and clean up) 
				job related activities. These functions will no longer be performed by the user running the GWE daemon.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-73">
				Relocated user workspace to user's home directory in cluster head node.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.6.1-alpha" date="02-28-2008" description="Second Alpha Release. Feature and maintenance release.">
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update">
				Changed scripts naming conventions. All command scripts have been renamed with the prefix 
				"gwe-cmd" and all utility type of scripts have been renamed with "gwe-util".
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-52">
				Generic download manager framework to stage files. Includes garbage collection and file caching.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-4">
				Virtual file system sandbox per user to stage files. Built on top of new generic download manager framework.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-53">
				Order life cycle hooks to start processing in a particular cluster and clean up after done. 
				This was only available at the job level before. Concrete usage allocates a download manager 
				for file staging of an order and delete the virtual file system from the cluster file system
				once finished. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update">
				Renamed P2L as P2EL (Processes Parallel Execution Language) to more accurately represent it.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update" issue="GWE-12">
				P2EL interpreter robustness. Still in progress though.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="fix" issue="GWE-23">
				P2EL now accepts P2EL script files as a parameter for queuing orders.  
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-1">
				P2EL semantics to support float ranges.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-1">
				P2EL semantics to support optional range stepping information.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-47">
				P2EL semantics to support optional formatting and precision information for numeric value ranges.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add" issue="GWE-51">
				P2EL semantics to support stage file renaming.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="fix" issue="GWE-2">
				Fixed allocations disposal timeouts to respect the aging and laziness tolerance level of the system
				towards an allocated compute resource.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add">
				"Slicer Integration" module. See "GWE Tool Integration > Case: 3D Slicer" for more details its feature 
				set and user guide.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update">
				Removed, created and overall clean up of messages to be output in log files.
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add">
				Issue management system for the project. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add">
				Mailing lists for the project. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="update">
				Updated project site with an improved navigation, a feature list page, release notes, source code 
				browser and javadocs and other useful project information and reports. 
			</action>
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add">
				Progress documentation of the "3D Slicer integration" effort.
			</action>
		</release>
		<release version="0.6.0-alpha" date="02-11-2008" description="Initial Alpha Release. Complete infrastructure plus limited feature set.">
			<action dev="mruiz" type="add">
				Complete abstract infrastructure plus a limited feature set. Check features page for details. 
			</action>
<!-- 
			<action dev="Marco Ruiz" type="add">
				Spring based configuration
			</action>
			<action dev="Marco Ruiz" type="add">
				Grid file system infrastructure
			</action>
			<action dev="Marco Ruiz" type="add">
				Grid network connectivity  infrastructure
			</action>
			<action dev="Marco Ruiz" type="add">
				Grid resource managers infrastructure
			</action>
			<action dev="Marco Ruiz" type="add">
				OS Package Manager Framework
			</action>
			<action dev="Marco Ruiz" type="add">
				Client agent to execute tasks on the compute nodes
			</action>
			<action dev="Marco Ruiz" type="add">
				Submission profiles
			</action>
			<action dev="Marco Ruiz" type="fix" issue="" due-to="" due-to-email="">New feature</action>
 -->
		</release>
	</body>
</document>
