<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>GWE Project News</title><link>http://www.gridwizardenterprise.org</link><description>News and announcements of the GWE (Grid Wizard Enterprise) project</description><language>English</language><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2008 01:18:55 GMT</pubDate><lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2008 22:54:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title>GWE 0.6.3.alpha Released</title><description>GWE 0.6.3.alpha has been released. The main effort has been on P2EL (and GWE's P2EL interpreter); which has been formalized as an extensible language by adding a strict contract for semantics as pluggable constructs with well-defined compilation life cycles. The interpreter includes a framework to comply with such new contracts and all previous scattered semantics (as well as new ones) have been re-implemented as pluggable function handlers. This allows for a more robust compiler, intuitive and ease of usage and stronger development guidelines for extending P2EL. For more details check the updated &lt;{{{guides/p2el.html}'P2EL Guide'}}&gt;.
 
Also, full feature PKI (public key infrastructure) support has been added in this release (finally!). For more details check the updated &lt;{{{guides/config.html}'Configuration Guide'}}&gt;.
 
The complete list of changes for this release can be found in the &lt;{{{changes-report.html}release notes}}&gt; page. 

The GWE daemon running on the &lt;{{{cluster/birn.html}BIRN cluster}}&gt; has been updated with this version, so if you have been interacting with this "GWE Enabled" cluster, you will need to update your previous GWE client installation. Check the &lt;{{{guides/install.html#Updating}'Installation Guide'}}&gt; for details on how to do such update.
</description><author>Marco Ruiz</author><category>gwe-core</category><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2008 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GWE 0.6.2.alpha Released</title><description>GWE 0.6.2.alpha has been released. It is a maintenance release, which mainly includes robust security features to guarantee users' sensitive information (such as keystore and file system) is safe guarded using the latest security technologies, such as sandbox user environments, MD5 based symmetric keys and AES encryption. GWE terminal has been revamped as well with lots of inline editing friendly features. The complete list of changes for this release can be found in the &lt;{{{changes-report.html}release notes}}&gt; page. 

The GWE daemon running on the &lt;{{{cluster/birn.html}BIRN cluster}}&gt; has been updated with this version, so if you have been interacting with this "GWE Enabled" cluster, you will need to update your previous GWE client installation. Check the &lt;{{{guides/install.html#Updating}'Installation Guide'}}&gt; for details on how to do such update.
</description><author>Marco Ruiz</author><category>gwe-core</category><pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2008 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GWE 0.6.1.alpha Featured at the NA-MIC's 2008 Engineering Review Week in Utah</title><description>GWE 0.6.1.alpha was featured at NA-MICs 2008 Engineering Review Week in Utah, to evaluate the value added created by integrating it with &lt;{{{integration/slicer.html}3D Slicer3}}&gt;. Useful feedback and feature requests (such as command pipelines) were collected.</description><author>Marco Ruiz</author><category>gwe-project</category><pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2008 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Slicer Integration Draft Released</title><description>GWE 0.6.1.alpha has been released bundled with a work-in-progress integration module to provide grid computing capabilities to &lt;&lt;{{{http://www.slicer.org/}3D Slicer}}&gt;&gt; by making accessible GWE features from within the Slicer UI. All the related details of this integration effort can be found in the &lt;{{{integration/slicer.html}'GWE-Slicer Integration' page}}&gt;. 
 
Also, for those interested in getting updates on the progress of this particular effort, a &lt;{{{mailto:gwe-slicer-users-subscribe@nbirn.net}slicer integration user's mailing list}}&gt; has been made available.

P.S. As with any command line based process, Slicer module invocations can alternatively be parallelized with GWE by using its &lt;{{{guides/user.html}generic tools}}&gt;. 
</description><author>Marco Ruiz</author><category>gwe-slicer</category><pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2008 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Collaboration Tools Enhancements</title><description>The following tasks have been completed to ease project collaboration:
 
* Documentation (up-to-date with GWE 0.6.1.alpha release) all over the project site has been added and updated. A useful &lt;{{{features.html}features page}}&gt; have been created as part of it. 
 
* The navigation of the project site has been revamped with a more self explanatory and cohesive sections.

* A &lt;{{{changes-report.html}'Release Notes'}}&gt; page has been created and will be used from now on to keep track of changes among release.

 * A &lt;{{{http://issues.nbirn.net/browse/GWE}'Issue Management System' (Jira)}}&gt; has been allocated for the project to keep track of ALL new feature requests, defects, general tasks, etc.

* &lt;{{{mail-lists.html}Mailing lists}}&gt; have been created for general users and specialized integration users to distribute topic related announcements. The support mailing list is as always present for users to communicate back with the GWE team.

* A 'Source Code' section has been added for the user to allow the user to browse through &lt;{{{xref/index.html}GWE's source code}}&gt; and through different useful reports derived from it.
</description><author>Marco Ruiz</author><category>gwe-project</category><pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2008 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GWE 0.6.1.alpha Released</title><description>GWE 0.6.1.alpha has been released. It includes fixes, improvements and new features as requested and prioritized by the test bed group. Most user relevant changes lie in the P2EL module; which has been leaped forward in terms of feature set and robustness (the details can be found in the updated &lt;{{{guides/p2el.html}P2EL Guide}}&gt;). The complete list of changes for this release can be found in the new &lt;{{{changes-report.html}release notes}}&gt; page. 
 
As part of the test bed phase, the GWE daemon running on the &lt;{{{cluster/birn.html}BIRN cluster}}&gt; has been updated with this version, so you need to update your previous GWE client installation if you are interacting with this "GWE Enabled" cluster. Check the &lt;{{{guides/install.html#Updating}'Installation Guide'}}&gt; for details on how to do such update.  
</description><author>Marco Ruiz</author><category>gwe-core</category><pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2008 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GWE 0.6.0.alpha Released</title><description>The first release of GWE is now available in alpha. A selected group of users have been invited to participate in a test bed created for the product during this phase. Although, the product is currently  available to the general public on "as is" basis. The product has passed numerous system load tests and major problems are unexpected. Still during this phase, it is recommended that all potential users take extra measures to back up and secure the data they will require GWE to manipulate.</description><author>Marco Ruiz</author><category>gwe-core</category><pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2008 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GWE Installation and User Guides Ready for Alpha</title><description>The guides to instruct how to install and use GWE has been published in the project site in preparation for first alpha release.</description><author>Marco Ruiz</author><category>gwe-project</category><pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2008 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GWE Project Website Online</title><description>The project's website is now online. A general terminology glossary is under construction.</description><author>Marco Ruiz</author><category>gwe-project</category><pubDate>Mon, 03 Dec 2007 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>